<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Storage on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/tags/storage/</link><description>Recent content in Storage on Grex</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>The MIT License (MIT) Copyright © 2025 UM-Grex</copyright><atom:link href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/tags/storage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Data sharing</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/storage/data-sharing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/storage/data-sharing/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='data-sharing'&gt;Data Sharing&lt;a href='#data-sharing' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By default, data on Grex are owned by the user and are not accessible to other Grex users or to external parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In research, it’s often necessary to share datasets or code within a research group or with collaborating groups. This documentation explains how to share data stored on a specific HPC system, in this case, Grex. Sharing data outside the HPC system can be done through other methods, such as Globus or MS OneDrive.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Connecting to OneDrive using Rclone</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/one-drive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/one-drive/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='um-onedrive'&gt;UM OneDrive&lt;a href='#um-onedrive' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Manitoba provides &lt;a
 href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-ca/microsoft-365/onedrive/onedrive-for-business"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Microsoft OneDrive&lt;/a
&gt;
 to its users as part of the Microsoft Office 365 contract.
While not suited, for performance reasons, for online computation work or for storing large datasets, OneDrive can be a useful storage space to store important data of smaller size, documents, articles and such.
It also offers some data preservation features like data recovery and data history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please also refer to &lt;a
 href="https://umanitoba.ca/information-services-technology/sites/information-services-technology/files/2022-05/data-security-classification.pdf"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;UM Data Security Classification&lt;/a
&gt;
 to learn which kinds of data can be stored where.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Data transfers for OpenStack Object Storage</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/object-storage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/object-storage/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='what-is-object-storage'&gt;What is Object Storage&lt;a href='#what-is-object-storage' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Object storage is a storage technology that allows large amounts of data to be stored as “objects.” This differs from a traditional POSIX-compliant filesystem, which organizes data as randomly accessible “files” and “directories” on block-based storage. Object storage enables access to entire objects only (for loading, storing, or retrieving). Each object contains the data itself (e.g., a photo, video, or document), metadata that describes the object, and a unique identifier used to retrieve it. Access to the content inside an object is typically handled by client software.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>