<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Visualization on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/tags/visualization/</link><description>Recent content in Visualization on Grex</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>The MIT License (MIT) Copyright © 2025 UM-Grex</copyright><atom:link href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/tags/visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Desktops</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/desktops/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/desktops/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='introduction'&gt;Introduction&lt;a href='#introduction' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the menu &lt;strong&gt;Interactive Apps&lt;/strong&gt;, it is possible to start a given application and use it for interactive work. Some applications have already predefined settings, like the slurm partition and allow only to adjust the wall time. As an example, the &lt;em&gt;Grex Desktop Simplified&lt;/em&gt; that uses by default the &lt;strong&gt;test&lt;/strong&gt; partition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start an application, click on the name of the application, then fill the required parameters for slurm (accounting group, partition name, number of cpus, wall time, email notifications, &amp;hellip;etc).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Custom Interactive Apps</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/interactive-apps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/interactive-apps/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='introduction'&gt;Introduction&lt;a href='#introduction' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the common applications used on Grex, we have addedd separate &lt;a
 href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/#interactive-apps"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;interactive applications&lt;/a
&gt;
 to make it easier for users. Some of these applications are: Gaussview, Matlab, Mathematica, Relio, Paraview, OVITO, &amp;hellip; etc. Some of the applications may not show up in your dashboard as they are protected with a POSIX group. For example, if you do not have access to &lt;a
 href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/gaussian/"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Gaussian&lt;/a
&gt;
, &lt;strong&gt;Gaussview&lt;/strong&gt; will not show up in your dashboard. Some applications like stata, metashape are commercial. Therefore, they are set only for the groups who purchased the license.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Servers</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/servers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/servers/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='openondemand-servers'&gt;OpenOnDemand Servers&lt;a href='#openondemand-servers' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using OOD, users can use RStudio, Jupyter, Code server &amp;hellip; etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these applications work in the same way as for &lt;a
 href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/desktops/"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Desktops&lt;/a
&gt;
 in the previous section. In other terms, before launching these application, a user has to set some parameters or resources to use (like the accounting group, slurm partition, number of cpus, &amp;hellip;etc.) before launching the application. Once the job is granted, click on the link with name _&lt;em&gt;Connect to &amp;hellip;&lt;/em&gt; to start the server. At the time of writing this documentation, Code server, Matlab Server, RStudio Server and JupeyterLab server are available.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>OpenOnDemand, HPC Portal</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='introduction'&gt;Introduction&lt;a href='#introduction' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
 href="https://openondemand.org/"title="OpenOnDemand" id="openondemand"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;OpenOnDemand&lt;/a
&gt;
 or &lt;strong&gt;OOD&lt;/strong&gt; for short, is an open source Web portal for High-Performance computing, developed at Ohio Supercomputing Center. OOD makes it easier for beginner HPC users to access the resources via a Web interface. OOD also allows for interactive, visualization and other Linux Desktop applications to be accessed on HPC systems via a convenient Web user interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the end of &lt;strong&gt;October 2021&lt;/strong&gt;, OpenOnDemand version 2 is officially in production on Grex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the beginning of &lt;strong&gt;January 2023&lt;/strong&gt;, OpenOnDemand version 3 is officially in production on Grex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since the beginning of &lt;strong&gt;February 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, OpenOnDemand version 4 is officially in production on Grex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more general OOD information, see the &lt;a
 href="https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.00622"title="OpenOnDemand Paper" id="openondemand-paper"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;OpenOnDemand paper&lt;/a
&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>