<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>How-To on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/categories/how-to/</link><description>Recent content in How-To on Grex</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>The MIT License (MIT) Copyright © 2025 UM-Grex</copyright><atom:link href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/categories/how-to/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using Multi-Factor Authentication (MFA) on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/mfa/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/mfa/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='important-notices'&gt;Important Notices&lt;a href='#important-notices' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As of January 9, 2024 MFA is enforced for all UManitoba/Grex users.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We appreciate your attention to this matter and encourage you to enroll at your earliest convenience to ensure a smooth transition. Should you have any questions or require further assistance, please don&amp;rsquo;t hesitate to reach out to your local HPC team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If some of your work relies on unattended connections or automations that may be disrupted by MFA, we ask that you do not enroll yet, and instead &lt;a
 href="mailto:support@tech.alliancecan.ca"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;contact us&lt;/a
&gt;
 for technical support, so that we can work with you on a solution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Please note that enrolling in MFA for Grex, makes MFA active and enforced also on the Alliance National systems as well, and vice versa. If this does not work for you, please &lt;a
 href="mailto:support@tech.alliancecan.ca"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;contact us&lt;/a
&gt;
.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id='multi-factor-authentication'&gt;Multi-Factor Authentication&lt;a href='#multi-factor-authentication' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Digital Research Alliance of Canada and our UManitoba HPC systems are using a multifactor authentication (MFA) system.
MFA adds an additional layer of security to the traditional password-based and SSH keys authentications by requiring a second factor, known as &amp;ldquo;something you have&amp;rdquo;.
The Cisco Duo product was chosen as the provider for this additional authentication factor.
Grex is using the Duo instance provided by the Alliance. The available additional factors and even the MFA provider are not the same as those used by the University of Manitoba for platforms such as UM Intranet and University MS Office products.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Connecting to Grex with SSH</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/ssh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/ssh/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='ssh'&gt;SSH&lt;a href='#ssh' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the work on shared HPC computing systems is done via Linux command line / Shell. To connect, in a secure manner, to a remote Linux system, you would like to use SSH protocol. You will need to have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;access to the Internet that lets SSH ports open.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a user account on Grex (presently, it is a Compute Canada (an Alliance) Account).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and an SSH client for your operating system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are not sure what your account on Grex is, check &lt;a
 href="https://www.computecanada.ca/research-portal/account-management/apply-for-an-account/"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Getting Access&lt;/a
&gt;
. You will also need the DNS name of Grex Which is &lt;strong&gt;grex.hpc.umanitoba.ca&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Connecting to Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='connecting-to-grex'&gt;Connecting to Grex&lt;a href='#connecting-to-grex' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to use almost any HPC system, you would need to be able to somehow connect and log in to it. Also, it would be necessary to be able to transfer data to and from the system. The standard means for these tasks are provided by the &lt;a
 href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_Shell"title="Secure Shell" id="secure-shell"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;SSH protocol&lt;/a
&gt;
. The following hosts (login nodes) are available:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;grex.hpc.umanitoba.ca&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;yak.hpc.umanitoba.ca&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;bison.hpc.umanitoba.ca&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;!--
 * bison.hpc.umanitoba.ca
 * tatanka.hpc.umanitoba.ca
--&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To log in to Grex in the text (or bash) mode, connect to one of the above hosts using an &lt;a
 href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/ssh/"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a
&gt;
 (Secure SHELL) client.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using Globus on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/globus/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/globus/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='introduction'&gt;Introduction&lt;a href='#introduction' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a
 href="https://docs.globus.org/"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Globus&lt;/a
&gt;
 is a service for fast, reliable, secure file transfer. Designed specifically for researchers, Globus has an easy-to-use interface with background monitoring features that automate the management of file transfers between any two resources, whether they are on a supercomputing facility, a campus cluster, lab server, desktop or laptop. Globus improves transfer performance over other file transfer tools, like rsync, scp, and sftp, by automatically tuning transfer settings, restarting interrupted transfers, and checking file integrity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Connecting to OneDrive using Rclone</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/one-drive/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/one-drive/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='um-onedrive'&gt;UM OneDrive&lt;a href='#um-onedrive' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Manitoba provides &lt;a
 href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-ca/microsoft-365/onedrive/onedrive-for-business"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;Microsoft OneDrive&lt;/a
&gt;
 to its users as part of the Microsoft Office 365 contract.
While not suited, for performance reasons, for online computation work or for storing large datasets, OneDrive can be a useful storage space to store important data of smaller size, documents, articles and such.
It also offers some data preservation features like data recovery and data history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please also refer to &lt;a
 href="https://umanitoba.ca/information-services-technology/sites/information-services-technology/files/2022-05/data-security-classification.pdf"
 class="is-pretty-link"&gt;UM Data Security Classification&lt;/a
&gt;
 to learn which kinds of data can be stored where.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Data transfers for OpenStack Object Storage</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/object-storage/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/data-transfer/object-storage/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id='what-is-object-storage'&gt;What is Object Storage&lt;a href='#what-is-object-storage' class='anchor'&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Object storage is a storage technology that allows large amounts of data to be stored as “objects.” This differs from a traditional POSIX-compliant filesystem, which organizes data as randomly accessible “files” and “directories” on block-based storage. Object storage enables access to entire objects only (for loading, storing, or retrieving). Each object contains the data itself (e.g., a photo, video, or document), metadata that describes the object, and a unique identifier used to retrieve it. Access to the content inside an object is typically handled by client software.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>