<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>How-To on Grex</title><link>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/categories/how-to/</link><description>Recent content in How-To on Grex</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><copyright>The MIT License (MIT) Copyright © 2022 um-grex</copyright><atom:link href="https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/categories/how-to/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Connecting to Grex with SSH</title><link>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/ssh/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/ssh/</guid><description>SSH # Most of the work on shared HPC computing systems is done via Linux command line / Shell. To connect, in a secure manner, to a remote Linux system, you would like to use SSH protocol. You will need to have:
access to the Internet that lets SSH ports open. a user account on Grex (presently, it is a Compute Canada (an Alliance) Account). and an SSH client for your operating system.</description></item><item><title>Connecting to Grex via X2Go</title><link>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/x2go/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/x2go/</guid><description>Graphical user interface access with X2Go # Linux (and UNIX) have a graphical user interface framework, which is called X11, X-Window system. It is possible to use remote X11 applications with the combination of SSH client with X11-tunneling enabled and a local X11-server running. However, this way is often quite slow and painful, especially over WAN networks, where latencies of the network really impair user experience.
Luckily, there is a solution for this, which is called NX.</description></item><item><title>Connecting to Grex and Transferring data</title><link>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/connecting/</guid><description>Connecting to Grex # In order to use almost any HPC system, you would need to be able to somehow connect and log in to it. Also, it would be necessary to be able to transfer data to and from the system. The standard means for these tasks are provided by the SSH protocol.
To log in to Grex in the text (or bash) mode, connect to grex.hpc.umanitoba.ca using an SSH (Secure SHELL) client.</description></item><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions.</title><link>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://alikerr.github.io/grex-docs/faq/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>