<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Software on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/categories/software/</link><description>Recent content in Software on Grex</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><copyright>The MIT License (MIT) Copyright © 2023 UM-Grex</copyright><atom:link href="https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/categories/software/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Running Gaussian on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/gaussian/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/gaussian/</guid><description>Introduction# Gaussian 16 is a comprehensive suite for electronic structure modeling using ab initio, DFT and semi-empirical methods. A list of Gaussian 16 features can be found here .
User Responsibilities and Access# University of Manitoba has a site license for Gaussian 16 and GaussView. However, it comes with certain license limitations, so access to the code is subject to some license conditions.
Since, as of now, Compute Canada accounts are a superset of Grex accounts, users will want to initiate getting access by sending an email agreeing to Gaussian conditions to support@tech.</description></item><item><title>Running Julia on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/julia/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/julia/</guid><description>Introduction# Julia is a programming language that was designed for performance, ease of use and portability. It is available as a module on Grex.
Available Julia versions# Presently, binary Julia versions 1.3.0, 1.5.4 and 1.6.1 are available. Use module spider julia to find out other versions.
Installing packages# We do not maintain centralized versions of Julia packages. Users should install Julia modules in their home directory.
The command is (in Julia REPL):</description></item><item><title>Running LAMMPS on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/lammps/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/lammps/</guid><description>Introduction# LAMMPS is a classical molecular dynamics code. The name stands for Large-scale Atomic / Molecular Massively Parallel Simulator.
Modules# Multiple versions of LAMMPS were installed on Grex. To see all the available versions, use module spider lammps and follow the instructions.
Available CPU versions:# Version Module Name Supported Packages 29 Sep 21 lammps/29Sep21 * 05 Jun 19 lammps/5Jun19 * 11 Aug 17 lammps/11Aug17 * 05 Nov 16 lammps/5Nov16 * 30 Jul 16 lammps/30jul16 * Available GPU versions:# As for the time when writing this page, there is only one version of LAMMPS with GPU support.</description></item><item><title>General Linux tools</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/general-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/general-linux/</guid><description>Linux tools on Grex# There are a number of general and distro-specific tools on Grex that are worth mentioning here. Such tools are: text editors, image viewers, file managers, &amp;hellip; etc.
Command line Text editors# Command line text editors allow you to edit files right on Grex in any terminal session (such as SSH session or an X terminal under OOD):
The (arguably) most popular editor is vi, or vim. It is very powerful, but requires some experience to use it.</description></item><item><title>Running MATLAB on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/matlab/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/matlab/</guid><description>Introduction# MATLAB is a general-purpose high-level programming package for numerical work such as linear algebra, signal processing and other calculations involving matrices or vectors of data. We have a campus license for MATLAB which is used on Grex and other local computing resources. MATLAB is available only for UManitoba users.
As with most of the Grex software, MATLAB is available as a module. The following command will load the latest version available on Grex:</description></item><item><title>Running NWChem on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/nwchem/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/nwchem/</guid><description>Introduction# NWChem is a Scalable open-source solution for large scale molecular simulations. NWChem is actively developed by a consortium of developers and maintained by the EMSL located at the Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL) in Washington State. The code is distributed as open-source under the terms of the Educational Community License version 2.0 (ECL 2.0).
System specific notes# On the Grex software stack, NWChem is using OpenMPI 3.1 with Intel compilers toolchains.</description></item><item><title>Running ORCA on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/orca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/orca/</guid><description>Introduction# ORCA is a flexible, efficient and easy-to-use general purpose tool for quantum chemistry with specific emphasis on spectroscopic properties of open-shell molecules. It features a wide variety of standard quantum chemical methods ranging from semi-empirical methods to DFT to single - and multi-reference correlated ab initio methods. It can also treat environmental and relativistic effects.
User Responsibilities and Access# ORCA is a proprietary software, even if it is free it still requires you to agree to the ORCA license conditions.</description></item><item><title>Running Priroda on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/priroda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/priroda/</guid><description>Introduction# Priroda is a fast parallel relativistic DFT and ab-initio code for molecular modeling, developed by Dr. Dimitri N. Laikov. The code originally implemented fast resolution-of-identity GGA DFT for coulomb and exchange integrals. Later it was extended to provide RI-DFT with hybrid functional, RI-HF and RI-MP2, and parallel high-level coupled-cluster methods. All these levels of theory can be used together with an efficient all-electron scalar-relativistic method, with small-component bases supplied for all the elements of the Periodic Table.</description></item><item><title>Running VASP on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/vasp/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/vasp/</guid><description>Introduction# VASP is a massively parallel plane-wave solid state DFT code. On Grex it is available only for the research groups that hold VASP licenses. To get access, PIs would need to send us a confirmation email from the VASP vendor, detailing the status of their license and a list of users allowed to use it.
System specific notes# On the Grex local software stack, we have VASP 5 and VASP 6 using Intel compiler and OpenMPI 3.</description></item><item><title>Modules and software stacks</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/using-modules/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/using-modules/</guid><description>Introduction# On a Linux server or a Linux desktop, software can be installed in one of the standard locations, such as /usr/bin. This is where most of the system-level software binaries can be found. For custom usr user-built software it is a good practice to install it separately from the standard location, to avoid potential conflicts and make changes and uninstallation possible. One of the common locations would be under /usr/local/, as ib /usr/local/My_Custom_software/ , or under /opt (/opt/My_Other_custom_software).</description></item><item><title>Using Python for ML on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/python-ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/python-ai/</guid><description>Introduction# Python is a dynamic language with many optional Library &amp;ldquo;modules&amp;rdquo; available. Moreover, Python is often used as a &amp;ldquo;glue&amp;rdquo; language for interacting with tools and libraries written in other languages (C/C++, Fortran, CUDA, etc.). This makes maintenance of Python software difficult. Not only do Python and libraries need to be of the right versions, but also other software they depend on should be of the same versions that have been used to build the corresponding packages.</description></item><item><title>Code Development on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/code-development/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/code-development/</guid><description>Introduction# Grex comes with a sizable software stack that contains most of the software development environment for typical HPC applications. This section of the documentation covers the best practices for compiling and building your own software on Grex.
The login nodes of Grex can be used to compile codes and to run short interactive and/or test runs. All other jobs must be submitted to the batch system. We do not do as heavy resource limiting on Grex login nodes as, for example, Compute Canada does; so, code development on login nodes is entirely possible.</description></item><item><title>Containers for Software</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/containers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/containers/</guid><description>Introduction# Linux Containers are means to isolate software dependencies from the base Linux operating system. On Grex, we support the Singularity container system, developed by a company called SyLabs. There was a fork of the Singularity project that produced a new project called Apptainer . As of early 2024, Singularity-CE by Sylabs and Apptainer by Linux Foundations are using the same SIF image format and thus are largely the same with respect to their usage and main features.</description></item><item><title>CVMFS and the Alliance software stack</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/cern-vmfs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/cern-vmfs/</guid><description>CC CernVMFS on Grex# CVMFS or CernVM FS stands for CernVM File System. It provides a scalable, reliable and low-maintenance software distribution service. CVMFS was originally developed to assist High Energy Physics (HEP) collaborations to deploy software on the worldwide-distributed computing infrastructure used to run data processing applications. Since then it has been used as a a generic way of distributing software. Presently, we use CernVMFS (CVMFS) to provide the Alliance&amp;rsquo;s (or Compute Canada&amp;rsquo;s) software stack.</description></item><item><title>How to use Jupyter notebooks on Grex?</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/jupyter-notebook/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/jupyter-notebook/</guid><description>Jupyter on Grex# Jupyter is a Web-interface aimed to support interactive data science and scientific computing. Jupyter supports several dynamic languages, most notably Python, R and Julia. Jupyter offers a metaphor of &amp;ldquo;computational document&amp;rdquo; that combines code, data and visualizations, and can be published or shared with collaborators.
Jupyter can be used either as a simple, individual notebook or as a multi-user Web server/Interactive Development Environment (IDE), such as JupyterHub/JupyterLab. The JupyterHub servers can use a variety of computational back-end configurations: from free-for-all shared workstation to job spawning interfaces to HPC schedulers like SLURM or container workflow systems like Kubernetes.</description></item><item><title>Running jobs on Grex</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/running-jobs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/running-jobs/</guid><description>Why running jobs in batch mode?# There are many reasons for adopting a batch mode for running jobs on a cluster. From providing user&amp;rsquo;s computations with fairness, traffic control to prevent resource congestion and wasting, enforcing organizational priorities, to better understanding the workload, utilization and resource needs for future capacity planning; the scheduler provides it all. After being long-time PBS/Moab users, we have switched to the SLURM batch system since December 2019 with the Linux/SLURM update project .</description></item><item><title>Software and Applications</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/software/</guid><description>Software# In the HPC world, software is more often meant as codes that do some scientific or engineering computation, data processing and visualization (as opposed to web services, relational databases, client-server business systems, email and office, &amp;hellip; etc.)
Tools and libraries used to develop HPC software are also software, and have several best practices associated with them. Some of that will be covered below. Without means to provide software to do computations, HPC systems would be rather useless.</description></item><item><title>Software Specific Notes</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/specific-soft/</guid><description>Software specific notes# This page refers to the usage of some specific programs installed on Grex, like ORCA, VASP, &amp;hellip; etc.
Software / Applications# Gaussian Julia LAMMPS MATLAB NWChem ORCA Priroda VASP Python for ML External links# Running jobs (on the Alliance&amp;rsquo;s clusters) SLURM documentation.</description></item><item><title>OpenOnDemand, HPC Portal</title><link>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://um-grex.github.io/grex-docs/ood/</guid><description>Introduction# OpenOnDemand or OOD for short, is an open source Web portal for High-Performance computing, developed at Ohio Supercomputing Center. OOD makes it easier for beginner HPC users to access the resources via a Web interface. OOD also allows for interactive, visualization and other Linux Desktop applications to be accessed on HPC systems via a convenient Web user interface.
Since the end of October 2021, OpenOnDemand version 2 is officially in production on Grex.</description></item></channel></rss>